Finding Aid for the Willard E. Goodwin Case History of First Use of Prednisone for Kidney Transplant Rejection Biomed.0040
UCLA Library Special Collections
Willard E. Goodwin Case History of First Use of Prednisone for Kidney Transplant Rejection
1960-1987
UCLA Library Special Collections
Goodwin, Willard E.
Biomed.0040
1.5 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
This collection documents the medical history of the first kidney transplant patient recorded as receiving Prednisone to inhibit organ rejection, in 1960-1961. Dr. Willard E. Goodwin, founding chair of the UCLA Division of Urology and surgeon of record on the case, arranged for transfer of these hospital files to the UCLA Biomedical Library. His reprint file of pertinent supporting literature on transplantation rounds out the collection.
Access
Portions of this collection are restricted.
Access to Series 1 (Official patient record) and Series 2 (Dr. Goodwin's personal case file) [Boxes 1 and 2] is Restricted due to patient confidentiality protocols; personally-identifying information from patient records may not be recorded or disclosed. Before visiting the library, researchers must first apply in writing to UCLA History and Special Collections for the Sciences, describing the research project and clearly presenting the purpose for which the records are to be used. For preliminary inquiries, telephone: 310.825.6940.
Series 3 (Supporting secondary literature) [Box 3] is open for research.
Acquisition Information
These materials were formally transferred from the Medical Records Department of the UCLA Medical Center to the UCLA Biomedical Library History and Special Collections Division in 1987 at the instigation of Willard E. Goodwin, MD, who was the surgeon in charge of this case. Dr. Goodwin also donated his personal case file and secondary materials to the Library at the same time.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9967092733606533
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 7 "volumes" (the folders were so labeled and comprise Series I) of physician and nursing notes, laboratory reports, operation records, etc. comprising the medical history of the first kidney transplant patient recorded as receiving Prednisone to inhibit organ rejection. Also included is the correspondence regarding the transfer of the case file to the UCLA Biomedical Library. Series II) consists of Dr. Goodwin's personal case file. Series III), Dr. Goodwin's reprint file of pertinent supporting literature on transplantation, rounds out the collection.
The case "volumes" are described as follows in the introductory case notes: Vol. I: Diagnosis records from first hospital admission, 1/18/60 to 1/28/60, and physician notes from subsequent hospitalization and operation, 9/20/60 to 2/9/61. Vol. II: Laboratory records, 9/2/60-12/1/60. Vol. III: Laboratory records, 12/1/60 to 2/9/61, plus Radiology and other reports. Vol. IV: Operations and doctors' orders. Vol. V: Medications, TPR, vital signs. Vol. VI: Intake and output. Vol. VII: Nursing notes and legal forms, documents, correspondence.
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1. Official Patient Record., 1960-1961. 15 folders
Series 2. Dr. Goodwin's personal case file, 1960-1987. 1 folder
Series 3. Supporting Secondary Literature.. 6 folders
Physicians -- California -- Los Angeles -- Archival resources.; Kidney Transplantation -- Case Reports; Graft Survival -- drug effects -- Case Reports; Graft Rejection -- prevention & control -- Case Reports; Prednisone -- therapeutic use -- Case Reports; Goodwin, Willard E. -- Archives
- Official Patient Record., 1960-1961; Series 1.; 15 folders
  Scope and Contents note
  Records relating the medical history of the patient from first hospital admission to death. The case file was officially transferred from the UCLA Medical Center Medical Records Department to the UCLA Biomedical Library.
  - Documents pertaining to transfer of case records, plus summary records regarding the patient., 1960, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    correspondence regarding the transfer request from Medical Records to Biomedical Library; minutes of the UCLA Medical Center Kidney Transplant Group for meetings on this patient, 9/9/60, 10/22/60, 12/14/60; case clinical summary; case death summary; Goodwin reprint from "Journal of Urology" 89(1):13-24, 1963, which includes description of this case
  - Volumes I, II, III: diagnosis records, physician notes, laboratory records., 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 2-7)
    each "volume" consists of two folders
  - Volumes IV, V, VI, VII: operations and doctors' orders, medications and vital signs, intake and output, nursing notes, legal forms, correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
- Dr. Goodwin's personal case file, 1960-1987; Series 2.; 1 folders
  - Dr. Goodwin's personal case folder., 1960-1965, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    notes and correspondence; carbon copies of case summaries, meeting records, operation report; telegram to WEG announcing patient's death; photos of kidney tissue sections, dated 4/10/62; correspondence with patient's parents, in which they express their appreciation: "we will always remember your sincere efforts and kindness towards our beloved..."
    General note
    Dr. Goodwin was the surgeon of record for the kidney transplant
- Supporting Secondary Literature., Series 3.; 6 folders
  Reprints from five different research/transplant teams, including Dr. Goodwin's, and from various other authors
  - Reprints by Willard E. Goodwin and team, Goodwin bibliography, transplant ethics. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Goodwin reprints on kidney transplants, 1962-1965; bibliography by and about WEG (447 items entries), 1937-1987; items regarding use of anencephalic infants as organ donors
  - Reprints by Joseph E. Murray and team. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Dr. Murray and colleagues worked at Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, Boston
  - Reprints by T. E. Starzl and team. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Dr. Starzl and colleagues worked at the University of Colorado School of Medicine, Denver
  - Reprints by M.F.A. Woodruff and team. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Dr. Woodruff and colleagues worked at the University of Otago, Dunedin, New Zealand
  - Reprints by Dr. R. D. Owen and team. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Dr. Owen and colleagues worked at the Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tennessee
  - Reprints by miscellaneous authors. (Box 3, Folder 6)